---
title: "1.6.1. Convention of Facilitation of International Maritime Traffic (FAL)"
read_title: "Convention of Facilitation of International Maritime Traffic (FAL)"
slug: "lesson-04"
estimated_hours: 1
learning_outcomes:
  - to analyse on a purpose and scope of the FAL;
  - to establish understanding on the importance of facilitating maritime traffic;
  - to categorise FAL requirements to be complied by a ship;
  - to distinguish the different types of documents required by the FAL;
  - to differentiate a meaning of the terms used in FAL;
  - to comment a new amendment to the FAL Convention which aims to address the need to combat illicit activities in the national facilitation programmes of Governments;
  - to present a new Maritime Single Window digital system, its implementation procedure and application.


links:
- "General information on FAL on IMO website, available at: [https://www.imo.org/en/About/Conventions/Pages/Convention-on-Facilitation-of-International-Maritime-Traffic-(FAL).aspx](https://www.imo.org/en/About/Conventions/Pages/Convention-on-Facilitation-of-International-Maritime-Traffic-(FAL).aspx)"
- "Convention on Facilitation of International Maritime Traffic, 1965, available at:
[https://euroflag.lu/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Convention-on-Facilitation-of-International-Maritime-Traffic-1965-as-amended-FAL-Convention-2.7.4-Recommended-Practice.pdf](https://euroflag.lu/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Convention-on-Facilitation-of-International-Maritime-Traffic-1965-as-amended-FAL-Convention-2.7.4-Recommended-Practice.pdf)"
- "Res.FAL.14(46), adopted on 13 May 2022, Amendments to the Annex to the Convention on Facilitation of International Maritime Traffic, 1965, available at:
[https://wwwcdn.imo.org/localresources/en/KnowledgeCentre/IndexofIMOResolutions/FALDocuments/FAL.14(46).pdf](https://wwwcdn.imo.org/localresources/en/KnowledgeCentre/IndexofIMOResolutions/FALDocuments/FAL.14(46).pdf)"
- "FAL.5/Circ.42/Rev.1, adopted on 1 July 2021, Guidelines for setting up a maritime single window, available at:
[https://wwwcdn.imo.org/localresources/en/OurWork/Facilitation/Facilitation/FAL.5-CIRC.42-REV.1.pdf](https://wwwcdn.imo.org/localresources/en/OurWork/Facilitation/Facilitation/FAL.5-CIRC.42-REV.1.pdf)"
- "FAL.2/Circ.133, adopted on 27 June 2022, “List of certificates and documents required to be carried on board ships, 2022”, available at:
[wwwcdn.imo.org](https://wwwcdn.imo.org/localresources/en/OurWork/IIIS/Documents/FAL.2-Circ.133%20-%20List%20Of%20Certificates%20And%20Documents%20RequiredTo%20Be%20Carried%20On%20Board%20Ships,%202022%20(Secretariat).pdf)" 
- "IAPH global ports survey on the implementation of electronic data exchange to conform with the IMO FAL Convention, available at:
[https://sustainableworldports.org/wp-content/uploads/IAPH-FAL-Survey-Report-Jan-2021.pdf](https://sustainableworldports.org/wp-content/uploads/IAPH-FAL-Survey-Report-Jan-2021.pdf)"
- "National legal regulation in Latvia in respect of port formalities is Cabinet Regulation No. 339, adopted 15 May 2012, “Regulations Regarding Port Formalities”, available in English at: [https://likumi.lv/ta/en/en/id/248453-regulations-regarding-port-formalities](https://likumi.lv/ta/en/en/id/248453-regulations-regarding-port-formalities)"


literature:
  - "Information on IMO website: [https://www.imo.org/en/MediaCentre/PressBriefings/Pages/FAL-46-amendments.aspx](https://www.imo.org/en/MediaCentre/PressBriefings/Pages/FAL-46-amendments.aspx)"
  - "Chapter 2.4 – The Digital Transformation of Ports in Theo Notteboom, Athanasios Pallis and Jean-Paul Rodrigue (2022) Port Economics, Management and Policy, New York: Routledge, 690 pages / 218 illustrations. ISBN 9780367331559. Available at: [https://porteconomicsmanagement.org/pemp/contents/part2/digital-transformation/](https://porteconomicsmanagement.org/pemp/contents/part2/digital-transformation/)"
  - "Ports and digitalization: what next? Publication by Holman Fenwick Willan LLP, July 2022, available at: [https://www.hfw.com/Ports-and-digitalisation-what-next](https://www.hfw.com/Ports-and-digitalisation-what-next)"

quiz:
  - question: "What is the purpose of the FAL?"
    options:
      - "To provide port State control inspections of foreign ships in port."
      - "To avoid a risk to arrest a vessel."
      - "To prevent unnecessary delays in maritime traffic."
    correct_answer: 2

  - question: "The FAL contains:"
    options:
      - "Standards and recommended practices and rules for simplifying formalities, documentary requirements, and procedures on ship’s arrival and departure."
      - "Standards and recommended practices and rules on human rights and fundamental freedoms of persons."
      - "Standards and recommended practices and rules for ship and cargo safety."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Declaration under FAL means:"
    options:
      - "Information provided in paper form, or, in exceptional circumstances, by non-electronic means to fulfil reporting requirements in accordance with Standard 2.1."
      - "Information provided by electronic means or, in exceptional circumstances, by non-electronic means to fulfil reporting requirements in accordance with Standard 2.1."
      - "Information provided in paper form and by electronic means to fulfil reporting requirements in accordance with Standard 2.1."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "Under FAL a Cargo declaration is one of the documents to be submitted to the public authorities in the port. Public authorities shall, in place of the Cargo Declaration, accept other documents provided according to FAL:"
    options:
      - "The ship's cargo manifest."
      - "Cargo stowage plan."
      - "A crew list."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "The Crew List shall be the standard declaration required by public authorities:"
    options:
      - "Containing information relating to the number and composition of the crew on the arrival and departure of a ship."
      - "Containing information relating to the number and composition of the crew on the arrival and departure of a ship and to the crew's personal effects."
      - "Containing information relating to the composition of the crew on the arrival and departure of a ship."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "In case of exceptional circumstances, public authorities shall accept documents conveyed by any legible and understandable medium, including documents handwritten in ink or indelible pencil:"
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Electronic certificates should be treated as equivalent to traditional paper certificates, provided that the certificates and the website used to access them conform to appropriate guidelines."
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Appendix 2 of the FAL Annex lists the declarations that may be required in paper form by the public authorities in exceptional circumstances. Which of the following documents is not included in that list?"
    options:
      - "General Declaration."
      - "Cargo Declaration."
      - "Ship's Stores Declaration."
      - "Crew's Effects Declaration."
      - "Advance electronic cargo information for customs risk assessment purposes as set out in the WCO Safe Framework of Standards."
      - "Crew List"
      - "Passenger List"
      - "Dangerous Goods Manifest"
    correct_answer: 4

  - question: "The correct explanation of GISIS is:"
    options:
      - "Global Integrated Shipping Information System."
      - "Guidelines to Integrated Shipping Information System."
      - "General Integrated Shipping Information System."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Actual time of departure (ATD) under FAL means:"
    options:
      - "The date and time when a ship leaves territorial sea of a particular State."
      - "The date and time when a ship departs from a port area of a particular State."
      - "The date and time when a ship departs from a location, whether from an anchorage or from a dock, in a port."
    correct_answer: 2

  - question: "Where any cargo identified on the Cargo Declaration is not discharged at the port of intended destination:"
    options:
      - "Public authorities shall permit amendment of the Cargo Declaration and shall impose penalties."
      - "Public authorities shall permit amendment of the Cargo Declaration and shall not impose penalties if satisfied that the cargo was not in fact loaded on the ship, or, if loaded, was landed or is to be landed at another port."
      - "Public authorities shall impose penalties and shall require to discharge the cargo in the port."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "According to the single window approach, the electronic transmission of required information shall be accepted from any location as long as the provider of the information has been certified and authenticated pursuant to the applicable requirements."
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "In respect of maritime corruption, the Governments shall encourage public authorities according to FAL:"
    options:
      - "To assess the risks of corruption associated with the ship-shore interface in ports."
      - "To identify risks of corruption associated with the ship-shore interface in ports for emergency cases only."
      - "To require the statement from the master that the master has not faced any evidence on the possible corruption associated with the ship-shore interface in ports."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Stowaway under FAL means:"
    options:
      - "Person who is secreted on a ship, or in cargo which is subsequently loaded on the ship, without the consent of the shipowner or the master or any other responsible person and who is detected on board the ship after it has departed from a port, or in the cargo while unloading it in the port of arrival."
      - "Person who is secreted on a ship, or in cargo which is subsequently loaded on the ship, with the consent of the shipowner or the master or any other responsible person and who is detected on board the ship after it has departed from a port, or in the cargo while unloading it in the port of arrival."
      - "Person who is secreted on a ship, or in cargo which is subsequently loaded on the ship, without the consent of the shipowner or the master or any other responsible person and who is detected on board the ship before the ship has left a port."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "Declarations could be transmitted separately or in a combined electronic format according to the requirements of the electronic data exchange system."
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "After individual presentation of passports or official documents of identity accepted in their place, public authorities shall:"
    options:
      - "Hand back such documents immediately after examination rather than withholding them for the purpose of obtaining additional control, unless there is some obstacle to the admission of a passenger to the territory."
      - "Hand back such documents before the ship’s departure."
      - "Hand back such documents after withholding them for the purpose of obtaining additional control, unless there is some obstacle to the admission of a passenger to the territory."
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "In case of consecutive calls at two or more ports in the same State:"
    options:
      - "As per procedures carried out on the arrival of a ship at the first port of call in a territory of a State, shipowners shall be obliged to declare required information to all ports of a State."
      - "As per procedures carried out on the arrival of a ship at the first port of call in a territory of a State, shipowners shall be obliged to declare required information once to the public authorities of a State."
      - "As per procedures carried out on the arrival of a ship at the first port of call in a territory of a State, shipowners shall be obliged to declare required information to every port of a State where the ship is arriving."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "The provisions of FAL conventions shall be applied in accordance with international protection principles as set out in international instruments, such as the UN Convention relating to the Status of Refugees of 28 July 1951 and the UN Protocol relating to the Status of Refugees of 31 January 1967, and relevant national legislation."
    options:
      - "True"
      - "False"
    correct_answer: 0

  - question: "As regards the limitation of shipowner's responsibilities:"
    options:
      - "Public authorities can require a shipowner to place special information for use by such authorities on a transport document or a copy thereof, unless the shipowner is, or is acting for, the importer or exporter."
      - "Public authorities shall not require a shipowner to place special information for use by such authorities on a transport document or a copy thereof, unless the shipowner is, or is acting for, the importer or exporter."
      - "The shipowner is obliged to provide the information regarding the entry or exit of goods known to the shipowner at the time of providing such data and as set out in the transport document that is or evidences the contract of carriage."
    correct_answer: 1

  - question: "Single window approach (An environment that allows the submission or provision of standardized and harmonized information and declarations to a single-entry point, typically by electronic means) is mandatory in all ports since:"
    options:
      - "1 January 2024."
      - "1 January 2025."
      - "31 December 2023."
    correct_answer: 0
---

**The aim of the Convention on Facilitation of International Maritime Traffic (FAL)** is to facilitate maritime traffic by providing a highest practicable degree of uniformity in the number and type of declarations required by public authorities with respect of the arrival, stay and departure of ships engaged in international voyages. FAL limits the number of copies of documents that can be requested up to the seven standard documents covering ship, cargo, passengers, as well, dangerous goods, postal requirements and health requirements. FAL defines standards, which are internationally agreed measures, necessary and practicable in order to facilitate international maritime traffic.
This is the list of declarations for ship arrival and departure:

1. General declaration (FAL 1)
2. Cargo declaration (FAL 2)
3. Ship's Stores Declaration (FAL 3)
4. Crew's Effects Declaration (FAL 4)
5. Crew list (FAL 5)
6. Passenger list (FAL 6)
7. Dangerous Goods Manifest (FAL 7)
8. Delivery bill for mail consignment as described in the Acts of the Universal Postal Union, the Universal Postal Convention and its Regulations currently in force
9. Maritime Declaration of Health (International Health Regulations)
10. Ship Sanitation Control Exemption Certificate or Ship Sanitation Control Certificate or extension (International Health Regulations)
11. Security-related information as required under SOLAS regulation XI-2/9.2.2 (MSC.1/Circ.1305)
12. Advance electronic cargo information for customs risk assessment purposes as set out in the WCO Safe Framework of Standards
13. Advance Notification document for Waste Delivery to Port Reception Facilities (MEPC.1/Circ.834/Rev.1)

The FAL **consists of 16 Articles and one Annex**. The Articles contain general provisions on the purpose and the scope of the convention, the entry into force of the convention, and on the procedure for adopting of the amendments to the convention and its Annex. The Annex of the FAL contains ‘’standards“ and ‘’recommended practices“ on formalities and requirements in respect of arrival, during stay and on departure of the ship.

The structure of the Annex is as follows:

1. Definitions and general provisions;
2. Arrival, stay and departure of the ship;
3. Arrival and departure of persons;
4. Stowaways;
5. Arrival, stay and departure of cargo and other articles;
6. Public health and quarantine, including sanitary measures for animals and plants;
7. Miscellaneous provisions.

There are three appendixes to the Annex of the FAL.
Appendix 1 contains the maximum information that may be required by public authorities for the declarations (Standard 2.1bis). Public authorities shall not require more than the information shown in appendix 1. Appendix 2 lists the declarations that may be required in paper form by the public authorities in exceptional circumstances (Standard 2.11) and they are following:

- General Declaration (IMO FAL Form 1)
- Cargo Declaration (IMO FAL Form 2)
- Ship's Stores Declaration (IMO FAL Form 3)
- Crew's Effects Declaration (IMO FAL Form 4)
- Crew List (IMO FAL Form 5)
- Passenger List (IMO FAL Form 6)
- Dangerous Goods Manifest (IMO FAL Form 7) (As required by SOLAS 74, chapter VII, regulations 4.2 and 7-2.2, MARPOL, Annex III, regulation 4.2 and chapter 5.4, paragraph 5.4.3.1 of the IMDG Code)

Appendix 3 contains stowaway details referred to in Recommended Practice 4.6.2. The 4.6.1 Standard of FAL states that the Contracting Governments shall require masters to take practicable steps to establish the identity, including nationality/citizenship of the stowaway and the port of embarkation of the stowaway, and to notify the existence of the stowaway along with relevant details to the public authorities of the first planned port of call. This information shall also be provided to the shipowner, public authorities at the port of embarkation, the flag State and, if necessary, subsequent ports of call. The Recommended Practice in this case according to 4.6.2 is that the masters should use the document as specified in appendix 3.

Since April 2019, the FAL makes it mandatory for ships and ports to **exchange FAL declarations electronically**. From January 2024, the **single window approach will** be mandatory in all ports according to the amendments to the Annex to the FAL adopted by FAL.14(46) on 13 May 2022.

The FAL has been in force since 1967 but is kept continually amended and updated by Governments at the FAL Committee of IMO. Latest completely revised version of FAL were adopted on 2022 by Res.FAL.14(46) Amendments to the Annex to the Convention on Facilitation of International Maritime Traffic, 1965, and entered into force on 1 January 2024.

Relevant national legal regulation in Latvia in respect of port formalities under FAL requirements is Cabinet Regulation No. 339, adopted 15 May 2012, “Regulations Regarding Port Formalities”.

To facilitate the clearance and inspection period for ships in port and in accordance with the formalities required of ships on the arrival, stay and departure of ships, FAL.2/Circ.133 was adopted on 2022 by the IMO FAL Committee containing a list of certificates and documents required to be carried on board ships.
IMO Global Integrated Shipping Information System (GISIS) module "Survey and Certification" provides information on electronic certificates issued by flag States and the relevant website links for verification of authenticity.
